<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest apology for the students of Edenburgh burning a pope December 25, 1680 humbly rescuing the actors from the imputation of disloyalty and rebellion with which they were charged in a letter, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>N. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M62</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13387</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13586528</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13586528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100556</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100556)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 465:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest apology for the students of Edenburgh burning a pope December 25, 1680 humbly rescuing the actors from the imputation of disloyalty and rebellion with which they were charged in a letter, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>N. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: N. M.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100556:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MODEST APOLOGY FOR THE Students of Edenburgh BURNING A POPE <hi>DECEMBER</hi> 25. 1680.</p>
            <p>Humbly Reſcuing the Actors from the Imputation of Diſloyalty and Rebellion, with which they were charged in a LETTER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Manet altâ mente repoſtum</l>
               <l>Convitium Papae, ſpreti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> injuria.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway,</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row:</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:100556:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100556:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr.—</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Was not a little amazed when I received Intelligence by your laſt, of that ſudden removal, not to call it Baniſhment, of you with other Students from <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh;</hi> and the rather, becauſe I underſtand from other hands, that what you repreſented to me to be only the innocent divertiſement of burning a Pope, is interpreted by the Government to be no leſs than ſome formed Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or Plot, that may tend in its conſequences to the diſſetlement thereof.</p>
            <p>You may remember, that before you went, I gave you a hint of the <hi>Bigottry</hi> of the <hi>Scotch Presbyterians,</hi> and of the high reſentments they uſually have of the leaſt intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on what they call their <hi>Religion,</hi> and of the ungovern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of their Principles, by which they think themſelves obliged to promote it, and oppoſe what ever may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it, tho' by never ſo Tumultuous and Rebellious Methods. And that I gave you a friendly caution, not to concern your ſelf in any of thoſe kind of <hi>Freaks,</hi> and I hope that <hi>Item</hi> might have prevailed ſo far, as to have prevented your being engaged, at leaſt ſo deeply as others, in this ſo ill-reſented enterprize, eſpecially at ſuch a time when all occaſions are ſought for, all artifices are uſed (by thoſe whoſe intereſt it is) to precepitate thoſe who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Proteſtants, into diſloyal and mutinous Practiſes; and I would the rather ſuppoſe you have declined to intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle at this time, ſince what always was the true Proteſtant principle, is now ſo become their intereſt, that no provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſhould tempt them, no ſpecious pretext allure them to give their Adverſaries ſo very great, as well as often ſought-for advantage againſt them.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but you are ſenſible how much the murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the late <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> hath been improved to the diſgrace of the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> a fact ſo contrary to Pollicy, as well as Chriſtianity, that if evident proof had not laid it upon men who went under that Character, the Argument, <hi>cui
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100556:3"/>
bono,</hi> would have unavoidably laid it at the Papiſts door.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hamiltonian</hi> and <hi>Cameronian</hi> inſurrections are freſh in memory; and how the Popiſh party have improved them to their advantage, cannot be forgot; ſo that why you ſhould enter into <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> and ſo give jealouſies to the Government at ſuch a time as this, I cannot imagine; for believe me, it is laid to your charge, that you not only covenanted amongſt your ſelves, but alſo <hi>combined with the Apprentices,</hi> raiſed Tumults, yea, continued them, and that by a violent oppoſition, after you were formally diſcharged by the Magiſtrates. For, I pray you, how durſt you ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon what you did in oppoſition to the Magiſtrates, unleſs you had the underhand aſſurance of ſome <hi>potent Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance?</hi> Nay further, as if all this had been a ſmall matter, as a note of diſtinction you put <hi>Blew Ribbons in your Hats,</hi> making that the Trumpet, as well as Colour of your Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and affronting the Nobility and Magiſtrates in the open Streets; yea, and as a piece of revenge, threatned to burn the Provoſts Houſe, which not long after was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately done: So that ſome are apt to think there muſt be <hi>other deſigns</hi> put into your Heads than meerly burning a Pope in <hi>Effigy;</hi> for if that were all (though even that had been unſeaſonable enough) why did you <hi>herd</hi> together in Companies, and not rather, being ſatisfied with what was already done, apply your ſelves to your Studies? Pray let me underſtand from you how things are in relation to this affair: For my part, I ſee no ſuch proportion betwixt the fault and the penalty, betwixt burning a Pope, <hi>and ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the Colledge,</hi> if there were no more underhand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in your enterpriſe than was at firſt pretended to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Loving Friend <hi>A. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100556:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOurs I received and read: I wonder not to find you take ſo much notice of a thing ſo <hi>Childiſh and Trivial,</hi> as was our late <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantry</hi> in burning the <hi>Pope, &amp;c.</hi> The mighty oppoſition it had the fortune to meet withal, is enough to make it conſiderable: But 'twas no ſmall ſurpriſe to me to hear a perſon ſo diſcerning as your ſelf, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being abuſed by ſuch <hi>ſorry Artifices,</hi> as our Adverſaries have made uſe of to make us appear <hi>Guilty.</hi> Were it not that I aſſure my ſelf, that your blaming us at ſo great a rate, proceeded from the want of a right Information of what we have done, and what has been done againſt us, it might go far to leſſen that high deference and value I have always had of your Judgment. I ſhall endeavour to diſabuſe you; The Interruption of my publick Studies afford me ſufficient leiſure: only let me premiſe, that I do not promiſe all that might be ſaid in our excuſe, nor, it may be, all that my ſelf could ſay were it convenient: The thing it ſelf ſpeaks, where I am ſilent; and I know that to labour it, were to imply that 'tis not ſo eaſie to Apologize.</p>
            <p>I doubt not, but that 'tis the Proteſtants <hi>Intereſt</hi> as well as <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> to keep themſelves within the bounds of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and to be careful to do nothing which may render them ſuſpected to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And I no leſs believe, that no true Proteſtants have any other Plot in the world, but to keep in their ſtations, and firmly unite together, and ſuffer the Papiſts, when ever they ſhall be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make an attempt, to <hi>ſplit upon the Rock.</hi> 'Tis true, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Proteſtants are too full of honeſt ſimplicity, to engage them in any endeavour, to work the Papiſts, or any of them, to ſuch a ferment as might precipitate them to any raſh enterprize, tho' they might foreſee never ſo much advantage thereby to themſelves, or the Proteſtant Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts on the other hand, tho' they have no <hi>Principles</hi> that will oblige them thereunto, yet ſeem to apprehend it as their Intereſt, to forbear to be the firſt <hi>Diſturbers of the publick Peace,</hi> if they can by any <hi>Artifice</hi> allure the Proteſtants to begin: And therefore they owning no ſuch ſtrait-laced Principles, no ſuch narrow, confin'd Chriſtianiy as that of the Proteſtants, are not afraid to make uſe of all the <hi>Privy Frauds</hi> imaginable, which may conduce to exaſperate them to any unwarrantable undertaking.</p>
            <p>All this, <hi>Sir,</hi> I readily grant you. And what advantage they have made this way, themſelves who are beſt acquainted with their ſucceſs, as well as conduct of their own Infernal intrigues, are moſt able to determine.</p>
            <p>But this we are ſure of, that the ſucceſs has not been ſo monſtrous great, as to render all other courſes unneceſſary. The <hi>Real Plots</hi> that they have cunningly made men, whoſe well meaning (if any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100556:4"/>
they could have) hath out-run their Prudence and Duty, to engage in, have not ſo much contributed to the <hi>Grand Deſign,</hi> but that there is ſtill ſomething left to be accompliſhed by <hi>Fictitious ones.</hi> We all know how induſtriouſly they indeavoured to affix a <hi>Sham-Plot</hi> upon the <hi>Presbyterians in England,</hi> and how little they wanted of laying the Top ſtone of that contrivance: But having failed there, they, like men whom difficulties and diſappointments do but animate, reſolve to practiſe upon <hi>Scotland.</hi> And purſuant to this Reſolution, they have there lain in wait, ready to improve <hi>every occaſion</hi> that might preſent it ſelf, where they might have the leaſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage</hi> to affix an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Sedition and Rebellion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> you only take notice in your Letter of the <hi>real Plots</hi> that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, or ſuch as pretend to be ſo, have been wheadled into by the Papiſts, and are pleaſed to reckon us amongſt <hi>thoſe Gulls;</hi> but you ſeem quite to forget the <hi>forged Plots</hi> that they would throw upon Proteſtants that are altogether innocent, eſpecially where they think they have got a <hi>plauſible pretext</hi> for ſuch an Imputation. Give me leave therefore to put you in mind of that part of their Diabolical deſign; and to aſſure you that the <hi>Colledg of Edenburgh</hi> is now one inſtance of it, amongſt others in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I proceed further, it will be convenient, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of being miſunderſtood, to tell you, That I would not in the leaſt inſinuate, that the <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> there doth concern it ſelf to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſo villanous an Intrigue, as that whereof I accuſe the Papiſts. No, God forbid I ſhould: They are perſons that have given ſuch am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo often repeated Teſtimonies of their zeal to the Proteſtant Religion, and of their great care for the preſervation of it, that there is not the leaſt ground for the moſt malicious and moſt diſaffected perſon to the Government, once to ſuſpect ſuch a thing of them. What I ſay is this, That ſome perſons there are, who beyond all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, in ſubſerviency to the forementioned devilliſh Reſolution of the Papiſts, have ſo <hi>miſrepreſented</hi> this innocent deſign of ours to the Magiſtracy, and ſo fly-blown it to them, as to make it appear quite another thing than what we intended it: And then I muſt needs ſay, the Magiſtrates could act no otherwiſe than according to the Information they received. Take this <hi>Item</hi> along with you, that I am not vindicating Diſloyalty and Rebellion, but modeſtly excuſing perſons not yet convicted, from thoſe horrid Imputations. And I do not ſee, that though the Magiſtrates have appeared againſt perſons, whom I endeavour to prove are innocent as to any diſloyal Deſign, and who, I ſay, were aſperſed as ſuch by <hi>the curſed malice</hi> of others, that I muſt needs be thought therefore to <hi>reflect</hi> upon the Magiſtrates <hi>ſincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as I would not have you think, <hi>Sir,</hi> I deſign to reflect on the Magiſtracy; ſo I would not have you believe I intend to <hi>Juſtify</hi> our ſelves, that we went on with our divertiſement after the Magiſtracy <hi>diſcharged</hi> us; much leſs that I concern my ſelf to defend every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular unpremeditated <hi>extravagance,</hi> which the violence of an <hi>unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected oppoſition</hi> might draw on. Let them who are better able than
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100556:4"/>
I, determine whether in the former we did well or ill; and for the latter, let it ſuffice, that I aſſure you, I verily believe, if we had met with no oppoſition, the whole buſineſs had been as unexceptionably managed, as 'twas innocently contrived: However, even as 'twas, I doubt not but to make it appear that 'tis great injuſtice to blame us, as if we did <hi>ſeditiouſly combine together with a deſign to give an avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed affront to Authority, and therein lay the ground-work of a more wretched Rebellion.</hi> When I ſhall come to tell you the great tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs we uſed, as little as might be to intrench upon <hi>Authority,</hi> tho' we went on with our deſign; and the ſubtil artifices on the other hand that were uſed to inflame us, you will eaſily perceive there was not <hi>very much</hi> in the whole management, but what might eaſily have been excuſed and <hi>paſſed by,</hi> had it not been <hi>repreſented</hi> through ſuch mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying Glaſſes, as 'tis more than evident it was.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid thus much, to prevent the wiredrawing of any thing I ſhall afterwards have occaſion to ſay, 'tis time I ſhould go on &amp; give you the Reaſons that firſt prompted us to undertake what we did; and as the thing was really firſt motioned by ſome of our own number without any <hi>forrain inſtigation,</hi> ſo were the reaſons, in a manner, <hi>peculiar</hi> to our own Circumſtances. We conſidered the great Progreſs our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Adverſaries made in their Conſpiracies, and that their deſigns were by this time ſo far advanced, that there wanted but a little more to put a Period to our preſent Government as well as Religion: For let none imagine that the PLOT is altogether disbelieved in <hi>Scotland.</hi> We conſidered, that we who look upon our ſelves as a <hi>Seminary of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> for the ſervice of Church and State, as Providence ſhall diſpoſe of us, had not hitherto given any <hi>Publick Teſtimony</hi> of our Abhorrence of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſuperſtition. We conſidered what diſadvantageous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations might poſſibly have been made in foreign parts, of the byaſs of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and we further conſidered what falſe meaſures may have been taken of us accordingly both at home and abroad, and how much the wicked Conſpirators might be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged</hi> thereby to a vigorous proſecution of their Helliſh deſigns. When we conſidered all theſe things, we thought fit at once to give an innocent proof of our own ſetled <hi>averſion</hi> to Popery, and alſo (as much as in us lay) to give the Lye to thoſe miſrepreſentations and falſe meaſures that have been made and taken of that Kingdom. And poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly we might do our Adverſaries therein a kindneſs too, by unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving them, and letting them ſee, that when they reckoned we were all of us ſuch blocks as were fit to take any ſhape they ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give us, they reckoned without their Hoſt.</p>
            <p>We reſolved therefore to burn the Pope; and we could not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that our enterprize ſhould be looked on as Seditious, much leſs Rebellious, becauſe it was carried on by perſons of various Intereſts and Inclinations, moſt of whoſe Parents are not in the leaſt <hi>ſuſpected</hi> to carry on any <hi>deſign contrary to the Publick Eſtabliſhment</hi> either in Church or State. Had it been only managed by ſuch, whoſe own, or whoſe Parents diſſatisfactions with the Government, whether Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical or Civil, might be preſumed to diſpoſe them to encreaſe Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100556:5"/>
and foiſter Tumults and Sedition to undermine, at any rate, what they diſliked, we might have ſuſpected poſſibly to ſee it branded with the odious imputations you ſeem to caſt upon it. We might then have thought that the diſadvantageous circumſtances of the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers would, with ſome ſhallow-headed people, have derived a Taint upon their innocent Deſign: But when we know that <hi>moſt of us</hi> who were concerned in it were <hi>fully ſatisfied</hi> with the eſtabliſhment by Law in our reſpective Kingdom; and when we knew alſo, that ſome of the undertakers had ſuch education in the <hi>Families</hi> of ſome, whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in the <hi>Affairs of State</hi> were ſufficient to free them of the leaſt ſuſpition of any deſign againſt the Peace of it; when we knew all this, we could not once imagine that our enterprize ſhould be looked upon, and proſecuted as a Crime of ſo horrid a Nature.</p>
            <p>We were the rather confirmed in this belief, when we reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the nature of the thing it ſelf; for ſo purblind were we, that we could not foreſee which way the Publick Peace ſhould come to be concerned in it: We were ſatisfied that there was no ſuch dependance between either the Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Government of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Church or State of <hi>Rome,</hi> as that an affront to the latter muſt needs redound upon the former. Some of us indeed could not but call to mind, that we have heard that our now Principal, once taking the liberty in the Pulpit to mention the vulgar ſuſpicion of the <hi>French</hi>-Kings illegitimacy, either had, or was in hazard of a ſevere reproof from the Magiſtracy for his <hi>unſeaſonable</hi> boldneſs; becauſe then there was a <hi>ſtrict Alliance</hi> between <hi>Great Britan and France.</hi> But we knew of no <hi>ſuch Alliance</hi> between the Three Kingdoms and the Triple Crown, and therefore did not fear, that a grating upon the latter, ſhould have affected the former by conſent: we thought there was not ſuch <hi>concord</hi> between them, that the <hi>beating upon the one ſtring</hi> ſhould cauſe the other to ſound by <hi>ſymphony.</hi> And further, if the Pope might be declared againſt in the Pulpits, and his Uſurpation abominated there without the Imputation of <hi>an affront to any of the Nobility,</hi> (and we have not heard that this hath, nor ſuſpect it ever will while his Majeſty lives, be proclamed Rebellious and Seditious) we imagined that in a way ſuitable to our years and circumſtances, we might ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a fling at him too, and—Burn him.</p>
            <p>And we had this further incouragement to believe our ſelves upon ſecure ground, That the very ſame manner of expreſſing a deteſtation of Popery, by Burning the Pope, has been practiſed in <hi>London,</hi> and in other places of <hi>England,</hi> without any <hi>Imputation</hi> of <hi>Diſloyalty</hi> or <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> that ever we heard of: And we were ſo fooliſh as to think, that what was permitted in a Kingdom (I may be permitted to ſay it) as well Governed as that of <hi>Scotland</hi> (ſaving that 'tis not in ſo Military a manner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) might alſo have been allowed here.</p>
            <p>Theſe, <hi>Sir,</hi> were the Reaſons that we had to undertake a deſign of this nature; theſe were the Inducements that led us, or miſlead us into a belief, that we ſhould meet with no oppoſition in the proſecution of it, but from <hi>thoſe of the Popiſh Intereſt:</hi> And we thought that if ſuch ſhould ſmell it before-hand, they would endeavour by all the <hi>Addreſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100556:5"/>
and Cunning</hi> imaginable, ſo to order matters, as to lay an obſtruction in our way; and therefore we thought fit to oblige thoſe whom we acquainted with the contrivance, to ſecrecy. How well grounded that fear was, the ſequel has inſtructed us.</p>
            <p>We feared likewiſe, that if the Papiſts ſhould come to diſcover it, and could not otherwiſe hinder us, they might attempt to do it by <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence;</hi> this ſuſpition was increaſed in us by obſerving the Marqueſs of <hi>Huntly</hi> was in Town, and that unwonted numbers of Papiſts, <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>French</hi> eſpecially, dayly reſorted thither; and we knew full well that ſome Students, who would readily <hi>promiſe</hi> their concurrence upon the forementioned inducements, might as eaſily be prevailed with after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon the proſpect of any difficulties to <hi>deſert us.</hi> For this alone Reaſon we propoſed a Paper to be ſubſcribed, wherein we promiſed our <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> one to another; for as on the one hand we were ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (if no interruption at all ſhould be given us) to engage as many Students as was poſſible, that the Ceremony might appear rather the <hi>unanimous</hi> acting of our whole Society, than that of ſome <hi>particular</hi> Students only; ſo on the other hand, we were reſolved, if the Papiſts ſhould have attempted us, to <hi>defend our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, <hi>Sir,</hi> is that <hi>Bond</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> which your Letter mentions: And (to deal ingenuouſly with you) whether our ignorance of the nicety of the Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> in this particular may have ran us into an error or no, I am not able to determine. I know that Kingdom has been ſo often burnt in the hand with <hi>Solemn Leagues and Covenants,</hi> and with <hi>Bands of Aſſociation</hi> and <hi>Mutual Defence</hi> upon all occaſions, that the Laws may poſſibly have arrived to ſuch a tenderneſs in that point, as to make it Capital for any number of perſons to ſubſcribe a Paper, tho' it contain no more than a mutual promiſe to meet on ſuch a day, at ſuch a place, to play a <hi>Game at Foot-ball.</hi> If the Laws be ſo, I acknowledg our Ignorance ought to be no excuſe. This I muſt needs ſay, if we were miſtaken, the <hi>Practice</hi> of ſome of our <hi>Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours</hi> here, and of the Students of <hi>Glaſco,</hi> and (I believe) that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the other <hi>Colledges</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> led us into the miſtake; for we have heard, that upon ſuch occaſions which the Students take to be of a general concern to them, it has been uſual for them to ſubſcribe a Paper of <hi>mutual Aſſistance;</hi> and the outrages which have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times committed in <hi>purſuance thereof,</hi> have never been ſo aggravated (that we know of) by the <hi>ſubſcription,</hi> as to cauſe them to be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on as other than a <hi>Boyiſh Combination.</hi> As to what concerns the preſent Subſcription, I do confidently aſſure you, <hi>Sir,</hi> that my ſelf, and all others, ſo far as I ever could apprehend, who ſubſcribed, took our ſelves to be obliged thereby to no more than to a <hi>mutual concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Burning of the Pope,</hi> and <hi>to a joynt defence of our ſelves against the injurious disturbance of the Papists,</hi> if they ſhould have offered any: And you will the eaſilier believe that that muſt have been the ſenſe of that obligation, becauſe at that time we could not foreſee that any of us ſhould be <hi>called in question for it by lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> Beſides, let any conſiderate man think whether the ſorry forfeiture of <hi>Half a Crown</hi> (the only penalty of that obligation) were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100556:6"/>
ſo great a matter as to engage any in a <hi>Rebellion:</hi> Can any man ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that if we had deſigned any ſuch matter, we would not have condeſcended upon a rounder ſum? Add to all this our <hi>peaceable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour,</hi> before, in, and after the <hi>Action,</hi> and what greater evidence can there be of the meaning that we took our ſelves to be obliged in? So that tho' I do believe in my Conſcience there was no one who could take it in a bad ſenſe; yet let's ſuppoſe that ſome ſuch there were, who being more Eagle-eyed than the reſt, did foreſee that ſome were like to be called in <hi>Question,</hi> and had a mind to lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their ſecurity, by obliging all to a <hi>mutual adherence</hi> to one another <hi>against Authority,</hi> if ſuch a thing ſhould happen; yet I am ſure they were <hi>diſappointed</hi> of their end, if ſuch they had; for to my knowledg there was none of them that ever attempted any thing agreable hereunto, either by force to <hi>prevent</hi> the <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of their Companions, (tho' there were none of us who did not privately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ruſhing in of Soldiers into the Colledge, and the breaking open our Chambers at midnight) or to <hi>Reſcue</hi> them after they were apprehended, or to <hi>defend the Statue</hi> till it ſhould be conſumed, or any other thing which might <hi>look like</hi> a forcible oppoſing Authority, otherwiſe than as I ſhall impartially tell you in the progreſs of my Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and how far that was ſuch a <hi>violent oppoſition to Authority,</hi> as you are pleaſed to accuſe us of, leave you to determine.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Paper, to prevent all miſconſtruction, we took care expreſly to declare that the <hi>reaſons</hi> of our Undertaking was <hi>not to put an affront upon any perſon whatſoever</hi> other then the <hi>Pope,</hi> and that that was the only end of it. For 'twas here only that we could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly imagine the Shoo would pinch, and therefore took what care we could to inlarge it in the Inſtep. And this is that I preſume which you intend by the <hi>unſeaſonableneſs</hi> you charge us with.</p>
            <p>However, our buſineſs was not ſo cloſely carried but that it got wind, and coming to the Lord <hi>Provosts</hi> ear, was quickly carried to the D. and L. <hi>Chancellor.</hi> Both of them are greatly enraged thereat, and theatning to <hi>cut down the Attempters,</hi> &amp;c. they reſolve by all means to prevent it; and in order hereunto the <hi>Town-Mayor</hi> is ſent to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of the Colledg on <hi>Thurſday</hi> at Midnight to cauſe him to interpoſe: the Principal accordingly, the next day came into the Schools, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a <hi>contrary Bond</hi> to be Subſcribed by the Students, which was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally refuſed by all, unleſs ſome of the firſt year.</p>
            <p>The next night the <hi>Town-Mayor</hi> being ſent again, apprehended two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen, and ſome others who were ſuppoſed to be the <hi>principal</hi> Actors. Theſe they carry to the Town-Guards, where they were examined by the Town-Council there met on purpoſe, and then delivered to the <hi>Gray-Coats,</hi> and by them under pretence of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the General, conveyed with Matches burning, &amp;c. to the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-gate Toll-booth,</hi> and there received and Impriſoned by a Company of <hi>Red-Coats.</hi> And hereby being put out of the <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of the Provoſt, there was no redreſs to be expected but from the <hi>Privy-Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100556:6"/>The next thing to prevent the deſign, was a Proclamation prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Merchants and Tradeſmen to ſuffer their Apprentices or Servants to go abroad on <hi>Christmas day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, for the grand reſerve, when the day came, the Provoſt contrary to the Priviledges of the City, ſuffered all the Forces that were in the Suburbs or parts adjacent, to March in, and Poſt themſelves in the moſt convenient places for preventing our deſign. Gen. <hi>Daliel,</hi> with the Livetenant and a Squadron of his Majeſties Horſe-Guard, and other Companies on Foot, goes to ſecure the Graſs-Market, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place of ordinary Execution. <hi>E</hi> of <hi>Marr</hi> with Two Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Marches towards the <hi>Parliament-Cloſe</hi> to guard the Croſs. And there indeed, as being the Gentile place of Execution, we deſigned to effectuate our purpoſe. The Kings Life-Guards ſeeing no appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ought in the <hi>Graſs-Market,</hi> March up the <hi>Castle-hill,</hi> fearing ('tis like) we would chuſe the propereſt place, and burn the grand Saucerer where the little inferior ones uſually were. The City-Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia are ranked in the middle of the <hi>High-street</hi> to defend it. Another Company of Foot ſent to double the ordinary Guards at the <hi>Holyrude-houſe</hi> for the ſecurity of the Duke's Perſon.</p>
            <p>By all this Martial preparation againſt us, all this noiſe of Drums, Kettle-Drums and Trumpets, all this appearance of Colours flying, drawn Swords, Matches burning, &amp;c. wherewith at this time the whole City was full, you will think, Sir, you had reaſon to charge us as you did with a <hi>formed Combination against the Government.</hi> Sure you cannot now imagine but that we were ingaged in a Rebellion no leſs formidable than that of <hi>Ireland.</hi> All this duſt could not be raiſed for nothing: It may be ſo. But you queſtion me, <hi>How durst we ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture our ſelves against ſuch Puiſſance, unleſs we relyed upon ſome potent aſſistance?</hi> Believe me, Sir, we intended ſport, and not to fight; and therefore had the courage to begin our March, not only without knowing of any <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> but alſo without being provided of any <hi>Arms</hi> our ſelves. 'Tis true, our numbers increaſed by an unſought-for <hi>Acceſſion</hi> of a great many Tradeſmen and Apprentices ſtill as we march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed along, who it ſeems were as eager for the paſtime, and as ready to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Popery as our ſelves: Yet I proteſt to you, that we thought our ſelves enow to <hi>rout</hi> all the Forces we came to fight, and to ſtorm all the Caſtles we came to <hi>beſiege,</hi> without the aſſiſtance of any; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we never had any former correſpondence, much leſs <hi>combination</hi> with theſe Volunteers. No, we never in the leaſt acquainted nor deſired the concurrence of <hi>any</hi> but thoſe of our own Society.</p>
            <p>We thus attended the Statue in its <hi>Pontificalibus</hi> down the <hi>High-School Wind,</hi> and up <hi>Black-Fryers Wind</hi> to the <hi>High-street.</hi> You will admire how we got any place free almoſt to perform the execution in: yet we did; but ſeeing the armed oppoſition that was drawing on all ſides, and being <hi>careful</hi> of keeping the peace, without further Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, than the reading of a ſhort Accuſation, we ſet it on fire with a couple of Flambeaus: at the ſight whereof <hi>Pereat Papa,</hi> being loudly reſounded, made it ſeems a terrible reverberation in ſome ears. <hi>L. L.</hi> being neareſt, was ſooneſt alarmed, and having been many years in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100556:7"/>
Kings ſervice, and (as they ſay) never drawn his Sword in anger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, now draws it in defence of the Pope; ſome who were near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, rudely demanded <hi>Hanſel,</hi> &amp;c. But this was not all, for making a furious paſs at one of the <hi>unarmed</hi> Actors, he loſt his footing, and unluckily fell proſtrate before the Statue. Some informed his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that it was a miſtaken Devotion, for the <hi>Timber-Popes had no Toes.</hi> So that ariſing, he commanded his Souldiers, who were but juſt now come up, not being able altogether to keep pace with his Lordſhips <hi>Zeal,</hi> to extinguiſh the Flames. And we who reſolved to make no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppoſition than by <hi>thronging</hi> together to hinder any acceſs to the Statue till it were thorowly kindled; after we had <hi>crouded a little while,</hi> departed, and left it to the diſcretion of its defenders. By this time it was all on flames, for we ſtuffed it well within with Roſin, Pitch, Gunpowder, and ſuch like combuſtible ſtuff, <hi>deſignedly,</hi> that our ſtay about it, after 'twas on fire might be the leſs. So that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve Sir, that however blameable we might be in burning it after the Publick Authority had appeared againſt us, yet we uſed all imaginable care that it ſhould be done in a manner as <hi>little offenſive</hi> as might be. After our departure the Souldiers did what they could to put an end to the burning. I doubt not but you would have ſmiled to have ſeen what <hi>cruel Drubs</hi> the merciful Souldiers gave his Holineſs with the Buts of their Muſquets; though the choice were hard, yet it was their kindneſs, rather to knock him o'th head, than ſee him die before their eyes, the unhallowed <hi>death of a Heretick.</hi> Yet could not all their care reſcue him from the deplorable Fate; for being informed of the Gunpowder, they thought it their wiſdom to retire, leſt by being too <hi>nearly</hi> concerned for the Popes ſafety, they might hazard their own. And 'twas well they did ſo in ſo ſeaſonable a time; for immediately the flames reached the Powder; and the Pope expired in a— Stink.</p>
            <p>But we have not done with him: A more <hi>Canonical Adventure</hi> yet remains: The little boyes of the Town, ſuch as you would have ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by their <hi>magnitude</hi> were ſcarce yet ſo well lettered as to ſpell <hi>Po-pe-ry;</hi> they take courage and reſolve to do ſomething: and finding the Relicts of the ſhattered head which the violence of the Powder had ſevered from the body, tye a ſtring to it, and drag it up the Street to the <hi>Castle-hill.</hi> The Kings Forces too miſſing ſo principal a part, and ſtorming to quit a prize ſo conſiderable to ſuch <hi>Diminutive enemies,</hi> like men of <hi>courage</hi> who ſcorn to be eaſily baffled, Troop about, and put on <hi>brave reſolutions,</hi> rather to dye like men upon the place, than not recover what they had loſt. Believe me, there was <hi>no great</hi> need of ſuch ſuperlative Valour, for the little <hi>Mirmidons</hi> had no ſtomach (I aſſure you) to fight ſo redoubted an enemy, if they could avoid it, and therefore retreat as orderly as they came: but their ſtratagem proved unſuccesful, for can we doubt but they had one? They had to do with <hi>old Souldiers</hi> who underſtood Martial Diſcipline too well to <hi>untwist</hi> while their enemies were in a capacity of rallying, and who therefore make an eager purſuit in <hi>Battalia;</hi> and falling in upon a ſmall party that was to juſtifie the Retreat, they diſcomfit them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100556:7"/>
and preſſing hard upon the main body of the <hi>Mirmidons;</hi> you may think for a while there was a ſharp rancounter! The <hi>Mirmidons,</hi> I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, ſhewed as much manhood as their enemies; but alas! being inferior, tho' only in point of diſcipline, after a tough reſiſtance they were forced to flye; but the rout was not ſo total, but that a party of them came off intire with <hi>half</hi> of the booty, which they ſecured in a Well, and after when the field was clear, took up and delivered to the publick Executioner <hi>to do his office upon.</hi> The other half of the Booty fell into the enemies hands. I think after ſome ſtrugling to whom it ſhould belong, one of the <hi>Trumpeters</hi> got it—!</p>
            <p>But enough of this. Sir, I am afraid you will ſcarce believe but that in telling ſo <hi>ridiculous a buſineſs,</hi> I impoſe upon you. I muſt confeſs I ſhould not have had the faith to have believed it my ſelf, unleſs I had ſuch grounds for it as I think could not eaſily prove falſe. But 'tis time to return.</p>
            <p>All this while thoſe Students who were apprehended on <hi>Friday</hi> night or <hi>Saturday</hi> morning, continued in priſon. On <hi>Sunday</hi> night the Kings Advocate, Sir <hi>George Makenzy,</hi> ordered thereunto by the Council, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen, Whether they were not <hi>inſtigated</hi> by Letter from the Lord <hi>Grey?</hi> They denied it. Then he asked, Whether they had any Letter of inſtigation from any body elſe? They anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, None. He proceeds, and, if they will not confeſs, threatens them with the Boot; an <hi>Engine</hi> which I who have been born in a Freer Air, may have leave without reflection to call <hi>ſlaviſhly barbarous.</hi> But at length finding them reſolved to adhere to their anſwers, and that he could not by any means extort any thing from them which could be ſo much as a <hi>probable ground</hi> of pinning the Contrivance upon the Lord <hi>Grey,</hi> &amp;c. he was content to take bond of 1100. Marks a-piece for further appearance at the Councils pleaſure, and to diſmiſs them.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Monday</hi> at night the Kings Advocate examined the reſt of the Priſoners, and threatned them with the Boot if they would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <hi>who writ the bond.</hi> One of them confeſſed <hi>he writ a paper which the reſt ſubſcribed, but denied it to be a bond.</hi> Then they were interrogated, <hi>Whether they deſigned an affront upon any of the Nobility?</hi> They anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That to prevent that very miſconſtruction, they had declared the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in that paper.</hi> Then the Advocate deſired him who had owned the Writing, to ſwear <hi>as to that clauſe of it</hi> wherein they proteſt <hi>againſt any intention to affront,</hi> &amp;c. whether any inſtigated him to put <hi>it</hi> in or no? He being conſcious to himſelf, that no body had inſtigated him to any part thereof, and not being <hi>aware</hi> of the <hi>ſnare,</hi> took the Oath as the Advocate had tendred it. Then they were examined, <hi>Whether there had been any of the Whig-Miniſters or Citizens at any of their Conſultations?</hi> And the Advocate finding by the reſoluteneſs of their <hi>denial,</hi> there had been none, was content to diſcharge them upon bond for further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, as before.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100556:8"/>Now might we have <hi>applied our ſelves to our ſtudies,</hi> and all things been quieted, had not ſome of the Soldiers (to what ends, themſelves beſt know) given us an <hi>occaſion</hi> (I do not ſay a reaſon) to <hi>herd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again,</hi> by aſſaulting and cutting one of the Students quite through the skull, before the very gate of the <hi>Colledg,</hi> and that without the leaſt provocation; and not only ſo, but by great indignities offered to others of us in other places of the Town. It ſeems it was a pity that things ſhould be ſo ſoon compoſed. Something further was yet to be done, to drive us on to a greater extremity! They that knew the humour of young Students, how unwilling they are to put up affronts either from Townſmen or Soldiers, and how apt they are <hi>to herd together</hi> in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and joyn in their mutual defence, could not be far to ſeek for a way to puſh them forward to things not otherwiſe excuſable than by the <hi>heat of young blood,</hi> and the <hi>inexcuſableneſs</hi> of the provocations.</p>
            <p>For my own part, when I conſider how frequent it has been for the Students in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and in other places of <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations to commit far <hi>greater</hi> outrages, I cannot but think that our <hi>Extravagancies</hi> at this time (tho' I am far from vindicating them) were extraordinary moderate. The truth is, we ſo far conſidered how much we were concerned at ſuch a time as this to avoid any thing that might have a <hi>mutinous aſpect,</hi> that I am confident we would have put up all thoſe indignities that were offer'd us, had not another thing which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervened, given us a much more <hi>ſenſible touch.</hi> 'Twas this:</p>
            <p>A little after the firſt diſorders were over, the Principal and Regents go to the Palace with a deſign to have made an apology to his R. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but being denied admittance (for the paroxiſm of indignation was not yet over) they return. But they go again, and are admitted. We were apprehenſive that they had in our names, without acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, <hi>made a ſubmiſſion, and begged pardon for burning the Pope.</hi> Theſe thoughts, I confeſs, galled us; and therefore to ſhew how much we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the ſame mind, we unanimouſly got <hi>blew Ribbons</hi> in our hats with this Motto, <hi>NO POPE;</hi> and went in a body (or <hi>herd</hi> if you will) by the Provoſt's houſe (which 'tis like was taken for an affront to him): When we were come into the <hi>High Street,</hi> we cryed, <hi>No Pope, No Pope.</hi> What perſons they were who might take themſelves further to be affronted by this, I do not know; or if any met with any real af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, they may partly thank themſelves. Sir, Lads are Lads, and will act as ſuch; and though we nor can nor will upon a deliberate refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on all that paſſed, juſtifie our ſelves in thoſe particulars wherein through the heat of a <hi>youthful frolic,</hi> we exceeded the juſt bounds of moderation; yet this we muſt have leave to ſay, for we cannot but think it, That thoſe perſons who pretend to exceed us as much in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and prudence, as they do in years, and yet could not forbear as <hi>unjuſtifiable</hi> provocations and returns on the other hand, have either forfeited that advantage of diſcretion they pretended to above us, or given us too great cauſe to ſuſpect they had a <hi>malicious deſign</hi> of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the Mutiny. I could give you inſtances even in this kind. We
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100556:8"/>
know who they were that threatned <hi>to tread under his feet thoſe who durſt wear a blew Ribbon before him.</hi> And who they were that cuffed and beat one of us (by what authority himſelf knows) for indiſcreetly ſaying, <hi>That all this ſtir was for burning the Pope.</hi> Perſons from whom (of all others) ſuch words and ſuch actions were little expected. I could tell you more. But my buſineſs is not to particularize other mens <hi>Extravagancies,</hi> but, ſo far as 'twill bear, modeſtly to apologize for our own.</p>
            <p>Sir, I do aſſure you this aſſuming to our ſelves Ribbons, is a thing that is done amongſt us every year, as a badg whereby we may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from others, and known to our ſelves: for you muſt know, we wear not Gowns and Caps as they do in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Univerſities. 'Tis true, we never wore ſuch diſtinguiſhing Ribbons at this time of the year; nor ever Ribbons with Motto's before. But what of all that? 'Tis no conſequence that we muſt needs therefore be ſaid to combine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as ou are pleaſed to ſuppoſe) to the diſſettlement of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menty; or that we deſign'd to make a party, and invite others thereunto to raiſe and carry on a Rebellion; And <hi>that this ſhould be the Trumpet as well as Colour of it.</hi> No; had this been our deſign, What ſhould have induced us expreſly to refuſe to permit the Apprentices to wear the ſame kind of Ribbon, when they applied themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es to us to that end? Or if other Gentlemen beſides our ſelves (or the Apprentices after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) did think fit to wear Ribbons of that colour, what was that to us, who could not hinder them? When you may ſee by this inſtance of the Apprentices, that we were ſo far from deſiring any to wear the Ribbon but our ſelves, that we did what we could to hinder others?</p>
            <p>However, when we ſaw by the impriſonment of the Printer who had done no more than barely printed <hi>No Pope</hi> upon our Ribbons, and by other aſſurances, how diſguſtful this was like to prove to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, we all pulled them from our hats. And if ſome one or two imprudent Students did afterwards reſume them, I may, Sir, expect it from your juſtice, that you will not blame the whole Society upon that account.</p>
            <p>And I hope to find the ſame Juſtice when I tell you, That ſome raſh inconſiderate Lad might perhaps in paſſion ſay, that <hi>the Provoſt deſerv'd to have his houſe burnt.</hi> Tho' ſuch words were not only without the knowledg and approbation of the reſt, but even condemned by the ſpeaker upon a ſober reflection; who I am perſuaded might ſay them without any premeditated deſign. You know 'tis uſual for one man in anger to tell another, <hi>He deſerves to be hanged,</hi> or <hi>he will be hanged,</hi> without ever intending to prove the Executioner. 'Tis true, if the party ſhould be afterwards found hanged in good earneſt, and no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given how it happened, there might be ſome reaſon to ſuſpect the Threatner.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100556:9"/>Sir, the Houſe was burnt, and burnt deſignedly, there is no queſtion: but how, or by whom, I am not able poſitively to inform you. I am ſure when I heard it, I was in a ſtrange ſurpriſe, knowing that it would not be eaſie for us to decline the odium; and therefore tho' I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of my own innocency in particular, and believed as much of all the reſt; yet for my farther ſatisfaction I was curious to go immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to the <hi>moſt daring and undertaking</hi> among us, and ſuch whom I aſſured my ſelf muſt have been concerned, if any were. But I pump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in vain; for I found them all in a ſurpriſe equal to my own, and as much deteſting ſuch a Villany. And I have reaſon to believe, that had they known any ſuch thing, they durſt have confided in my ſecreſie, tho' poſſibly had it been ſo, their confidence would have proved falſe bottom'd. And I am the rather inclined to pronounce them innocent, becauſe I found them all able, by a ſucceſſion of witneſſes, as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, to prove where they had been all that time. And tho' diligent inquiry has been made at <hi>Dyddiſton, Libberton,</hi> and other places adjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Prieſt field;</hi> yet I hear not of any one of our number that was ſeen any time that day or night thereabouts.</p>
            <p>And I could further confirm our innocency by the late report we heard, that one of theſe poor Boys hath been ſince booted: And tho' it might have been expected that the extremity of that horrible Torture might have made him accuſe himſelf or others of things that never entred into his or their thoughts; yet 'tis ſaid he aſſerted their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency with admirable courage; and being taken out, bid the ſtanders-by conſider how great that innocency muſt needs be, when it had ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him to undergo thoſe torments which he doubted not would have forced confeſſions of the greateſt of Villanies from the ſtouteſt of themſelves! But I ſhall rather ſuperſede this Argument, than once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve men could have acted ſo great cruelty upon children.</p>
            <p>Sir, that I may be plain with you, there wants not ground to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That ſome perſons might think if they could cunningly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly fire the houſe of <hi>Prieſt-field,</hi> it would be an eaſie matter to raiſe a belief that it was done by us. They knew that the circumſtances of the foregoing diſorders, eſpecially the words which they knew they could prove ſome of us in paſſion had ſpoken, would be evidence ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſuſpect, if not convict us of the fact, unleſs we could with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual probability lay it ſome where elſe; and that they hoped might be prevented by a ſecret management on their ſide. But whether or no they have thus managed it with a cunning and ſecreſie equal to the contrivance, poſſibly we may know more hereafter. At preſent, we know thus much, that there was a Gunpowder Barrel with the Caſtle ſtamp upon't, found the next day in that part of the Park that is near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to <hi>Prieſtfield.</hi> And as I am informed, ſome asking the Governour of the Caſtle, <hi>To whom, and when he had delivered any Barrels of Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi> received this anſwer, That <hi>of late he had not delivered any, but one to the Halyrud-houſe, to furniſh the Gaurds withall.</hi> But having this laſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100556:9"/>
particular only by flying report, I will not be poſitive in it: But be that as it will, I ſee not how we can once imagine how any of the Students ſhould come by a Barrel ſo marked, for that ſuch a Barrel was found is moſt certain: I think none will ſay they either ſtormed the Caſtle, or plundered the <hi>Halyrud-houſe</hi> for it. Beſides, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but have heard of the attempt that was made to fire a Houſe in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> 'tis like if the Incendiary had not been taken and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to be one of the Marqueſs of <hi>Huntlies</hi> men, we might have been charged with that too; and you have heard of the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Citizens at preſent have, that that wicked deſign of burning their City is not yet lade aſide. And the World knows that <hi>London</hi> was burnt—and by whom.</p>
            <p>I will not urge your Argument of <hi>Cui bono:</hi> If it be of any force, let it prevail only ſo far, as to make you believe us innocent, till you hear we are proved guilty. And let not a perfunctory reading of the late Proclamation in <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt us, cauſe you to miſtake it ſo far, as to imagine we are directly charged therein of this horrid Fact, much leſs already proved guilty of it; for tho' it be ſomething perplexed, yet upon due examination you will find, that 'tis only poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that <hi>there is convincing proof that the Houſe of</hi> Prieſt field <hi>was burnt down by throwing in Fireballs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deny not that we were accuſed as guilty before the Council, and (as 'tis like) that all the probable circumſtances were with the utmoſt induſtry <hi>aggravated</hi> in the Information, we may believe that nothing which the utmoſt malice of our Adverſaries could ſuggeſt was omitted, becauſe of the meaſures that the Council thereupon took: It was no ſmall thing which induced them to ſummon before them thoſe who had given bond for their appearance, and upon their appearance to Impriſon them again, and then to ſhut up the Gates of the Schools of the Colledge: And in the next place, by the Proclamation, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all and every of the Students within twenty four hours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part Fifteen Miles at leaſt from <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis (as I am informed) our Principal offered that thoſe who ſhould be found guilty of theſe diſorders, might bear the puniſhment themſelves; and thought it hard, that all ſhould be involved in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ruine, before it appeared how many were guilty: And knew not whether it was regular firſt to puniſh them, and then examine whether they deſerved it—And how this examination could be taken in their abſence—much leſs, whether a ſubmiſſion by proxy would be admitted:—And deſired his Advocates might be heard argue it, whether it were ſo agreeable to Law, that a Colledge eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Parliament, without Act of Parliament ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved?</p>
            <p>Sir, there is one thing more I muſt not forget to tell you; 'tis, that tho' the Proclamation take care, that ſuch whoſe Parents or Tutors
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100556:10"/>
will give caution for their good behaviour might abide behind; yet matters were ſo ordered, that tho' the Engliſh Gentlemen offered ſuch caution, yet the Clerks of the Council delayed firſt, and at laſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had been conſulting at the <hi>Halyrud-houſe,</hi> poſitively refuſed to accept it; and ſo the time allowed being near an end, and they fearing to be trapanned, were in all haſt neceſſitated to go out of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> on foot, and take poſt at the next Stage.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I have given you an impartial account of the whole procedure, ſo far as I am able; and tho' I do not pretend that what I have ſaid will vindicate us in every particular; yet this I may ſay without any imputation of Impudence, that upon the whole matter, 'tis evident our crimes are not near ſo odious as you have been made to believe. I may ſay it, had there been no oppoſition, nothing, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the contrivance or management of the whole Action, could have been juſtly lyable to blame. 'Tis true, we have been indiſcreet, raſh, have acted like our ſelves, in that when we heard of oppoſition we deſiſted not. I am heartily ſorry we went on, when we ſee, that what we were a going about, <hi>for the manner of it,</hi> was diſguſted by the Magiſtrates. But that we deſigned a Rebellion, were abetted by others thereunto, endeavoured to make a party to carry it on, to the diſſetlement of the Government, or that we did ſo much as avow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts to the Magiſtracy, is wickedly falſe. Even thoſe extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which we did commit, may moſt of them be accounted for, by the unexpectedneſs of the oppoſition we met withal, and the great provocations we thought we received from particular perſons. And 'tis no mean Argument that we are not ſo really guilty as your Letter would make us, if it be ſoberly conſidered that ſuch trivial, boyiſh freaks, were improved with ſuch a <hi>mighty pother</hi> to make us appear ſo. Who can imagine but that there have been exceeding falſe Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes uſed, when our <hi>Childiſh divsrtiſements</hi> have been repreſented to the Magiſtrates as <hi>formidable Combinations</hi> againſt the State? What a Mountain hath been made of our Molehill! Thus can men make eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Stake in a Hedge, when they have a mind to pull it up, a Publick Nuſance! Thus can wicked men who have an itch to be combating, make Images of Straw appear real enemies! Thus can they contrive to diſſolve Seminaries of Learning, when according to the old me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, they are uſhering in Devotion by Ignorance! Good God! what terrible <hi>Batteries</hi> may we not expect, when ſuch extraordinary dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence is uſed already to <hi>force earth</hi> for <hi>the Mounts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, God bleſs His Majeſty ſay I, and let him live to diſappoint the Malice and Hopes of his greateſt Enemies; for we may poſſibly have ſuch a Succeſſour, who is reſolved to look upon peoples <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their deteſtation of Popery</hi> to be a <hi>Crime equal to Rebellion:</hi> And every publick owning of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> to be an intollerable <hi>affront to his Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100556:10"/>Sir, 'tis time I conclude; If I have been already too tedious, you will aſcribe it to the zeal I have at once to ſatisfie your commands, and to waſh of thoſe black and horrid imputations which your Letter involves me and others in. I ſhould be ſorry that your ſelf, or any other conſiderate perſon ſhould take <hi>me</hi> to be guilty of that <hi>Bigottry</hi> you ſpeak of, much more ſorry to ſee you continue to think me ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of thoughts of Rebellion: You know how much I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, ſince I underſtood the difference of any thing, deteſted thoſe both Principles and Practiſes. I am intirely of your mind, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants cannot more prejudice themſelves, and the intereſt of their Religion, then by endeavouring to promote it by undue courſes, or to defend and ſecure it by aſſociations not warranted by Law. If by all I have ſaid, I have been able to reſcue my Loyalty from that taint it may have received in your opinion, upon the account of my being in ſome meaſure concerned in what you ſo highly decry; 'twill be the greateſt ſatisfaction imaginable to</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> 168<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The devouteſt of your Servants</hi> N. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
